Inventory of the Rev. Samuel Huntting Sayre, Jr. Papers 1874-1989
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- (4)
  - Ministry, 1903-1979 (4)
    - Ministry - Published Material written by Samuel H. Sayre, 1922, 1925, 1926, 1952, 1973, 1978 and 1979 (4, 24)
      Part of a St. John's Church Bulletin that has a picture of and an article by Samuel H. Sayre concerning his summers in the West. January, 15, 1922.
      The Living Church article by Samuel H. Sayre entitled "The Church and Government Hospitals." April 25, 1925.
      St. Andrew's Cross article by Samuel Huntting Sayre, "Wanted: A Man" about needing people for missions in the West. (1926).
      The New Age article "The Word "˜Catholic'" in June 1952 issue.
      The Living Church editorial published August 19, 1973.
      The Living Church, January 29, 1978
      Per note on cover, the important items in this issue are "a letter to Aunt Josephine and my letter to the Editor".
      The Living Church editorial, "The Old Days in South Dakota" published April 9, 1978.
      The Living Church editorial, "Loves TLC" published February 25, 1979.
    - Ministry - St. Barnabus Church, 1939, 1944, 1952 and undated (4, 25)
      1939 Easter Communicant List
      Photographs, Easter 1941.
      1944 label offering reduction of Parish debt
      1952 invitation.
      Addresses of Parishioners from St. Barnabus Church.
    - Ministry - St. James Mission, 1926 (4, 26)
      Letter from Rev. William Westover about the history of St. James Mission in Mobridge, South Dakota.
    - Ministry - St. Mary's Church, 1930 (4, 27)
      July 1, 1930 letter about St. Mary's Church 50th Anniversary.
    - Ministry - Tau Delta Alpha Sorority and Pi Alpha Fraternity, undated. (4, 28)
      Notation on front of manila envelope says "This should be kept in case that Pi Alpha Fraternity and Tau Delta Alpha should ever be reinstated as a national church organization. Pi Alpha ritual book str in box in pump house."
      Guide entitled Ritual of the Tau Delta Alpha Sorority undated.
      Authorization for St. Barnabas Church, Eagle Rock, Los Angeles, California to be part of the Los Angeles Alpha Chapter. Undated.
    - Ministry - Woman's Auxiliary, 1952 (4, 29)
      1952 Annual Report of the Woman's Auxiliary to the National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church in the United States of America, Diocese of Los Angeles.
      1952 Officers' Handbook of Diocese of Arkansas
    Series 7: Sermons
  - Sermons, 1905, 1924, 1932, 1934, 1936, 1939 and 1975 and undated (4)
    This series has been divided into sermons given by Rev. Sayre and sermons given by other ministers.
      Subseries 1: Sermons by Samuel H. Sayre
    - Sermons by Samuel H. Sayre, 1905, 1924, 1932, 1934, 1936 and undated (4, 1)
      Rev. Sayre's sermons arrived loose, and have been grouped by date, if dated, by number, if numbered, and by size of paper if undated. The sermons by others might include some sermons by Rev. Sayre.
      - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Sermons (Dated), 1905, 1924, 1932, 1934, and 1936 (4, 1, 30)
      - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Sermons (Notes), Undated (4, 1, 31)
        Notes by Rev. Samuel H. Sayre.
      - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Sermons (Numbered), undated (4, 1, 32)
        These sermons have been numbered by Rev. Sayre.
      - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Sermons, Undated (4, 1, 33)
        Folder one of two that contain undated sermons.
      - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Sermons, Undated (4, 1, 34)
        Folder two of two that contain undated sermons.
      Subseries 2: Sermons by Others
    - Sermons by Others, 1935-1939, 1975 and undated (4, 2)
      These papers appear to be notes, outlines and full copies of sermons given by other ministers. Some of them could possibly be sermons given by Samuel H. Sayre. Some of the papers have a topic written along the top margin and note hymns sung. It is difficult to tell if the original order was by these topics, by date order, or another order, but they have been placed in date order.
      Because of the fragile condition of the paper on which these notes are handwritten, some of them have been photocopied. The originals are filed with the photocopies.
      Some of the names on the papers who are noted as deliverers of a sermon include Rev. Belliss, Rev. Bonacker, Rev. Holmes, Rev. Walker, Rev. White and others. Rev. F.C. Benson Belliss, Rev. Ralph Bonacker and Rev. Pierce Butler were the clergy for St. Paul's Church in Chicago, Illinois in the Summer of 1938.
      - 1935 (4, 2, 35)
      - 1936 (4, 2, 36)
      - 1937 (4, 2, 37)
      - 1938 (4, 2, 38)
      - 1939 (4, 2, 39)
      - 1975 and undated, undated (4, 2, 40)
        Sermon entitled "An Instructed Eucharist", undated but "received 10/31/1975".
        Sermon by Rev. Conrad H. Goodwin at St. John's in Hampton, Virginia on August 18, but no year noted.
- (5)
    Series 8: Diaries
  - Diaries, 1918-1952 and 1959-1963 (5)
    The 1918 to 1963 diaries tell mainly of Rev. Sayre's day to day activities and usually include letters he has written and received, where he gone, when he naps, and people he meets if they include family and close friends. He often notes where he eats his meals, what time he rises, and what he is reading. After his marriage in 1938, his entries become a little fuller. When he is visiting his family, he goes into a little more detail, but still sticks to the facts. His train and automobile trips across country are usually interesting. Very rarely does he share his feelings, though he might comment if a letter was wonderful, a meal great, a death hard on a family or how great it is to be back at college or at his old home or with Marjorie after a separation. There are addresses, notes, accounts, Christmas lists and book lists in the back of many of the early diaries. In most of the diaries, he will note in the top margin if he changes locations, particularly for an overnight stay or a trip and when he moves. Years 1953 to October 1, 1959 are missing.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1918 (5, 1)
      He is in the U.S. Naval Reserve Force, stationed near Hampton, and is discharged on August 28, 1919. Throughout the year, he has dental problems plus has his appendix removed in June.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1919 (5, 2)
      He begins college at St. Stephens on August 18, 1919. He tells about his classes and grades and his membership in Tu Sigma Alpha Epsilon. St. Stephens College is now Bard College.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1920 (5, 3)
      He is at St. Stephens during the school year and goes to Camp Houghteling and Mobridge, South Dakota during the summer.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1921 (5, 4)
      He is at St. Stephens during the school year and completes his studies. He goes to Mobridge and Fort Yates, South Dakota during the summer.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1922 (5)
      September 26, 1922, Rev. Sayre enters the General Theological Seminary in New York City as a candidate for the ministry under Bishop Burleson and spends his summer in Sioux Falls, South Dakota doing missionary work.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1923 (5, 6)
      He is at General Theological Seminary in New York City during the school year and at Church of Incarnation, Dallas, South Dakota during the summer. He preaches his first sermon on June 24, 1923.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1924 (5, 7)
      He is at General Theological Seminary in New York City during the school year and spends the summer in Hampton and visiting relatives.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1925 (5, 8)
      He is at General Theological Seminary in New York City during the school year. On April 19, 1925 he is ordained a Deacon at St. John's Church in Hampton, Virginia by Bishop Burleson, the bishop of South Dakota. August 2, 1925 is his first Sunday in his First Parish in Mobridge, South Dakota. He meets Marjorie Renison, his future wife, sometime in the fall.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1926 (5, 9)
      On March 6, 1926 he mentions his feelings for "Miss Renison". He is ordained by Rt. Rev. Arthur Conover Thompson at St. John's Church in Hampton, Virginia on March 18, 1926. At St. John's Church, he celebrates his first Holy Eucharist as a Priest on March 21, 1926. He writes on April 5 that he "sealed his engagement with Miss Marjorie Renison".
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1927 (5, 10)
      In April he left South Dakota to go assist Dr. George Thomas of St. Paul's Church in Kenwood, Chicago, Illinois. On April 7, 1927 he notes on top margin, "Important - my ideas"¦"
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1928 (5, 11)
      January 31 was Rev. Sayre's last day at St. Paul's Church.
      March 5 Rev. Sayre received official call from St. Mary's Church, Williamsport, Pennsylvania and The Church of Our Saviour in Montoursville, Pennsylvania.
      April 1 Rev. Sayre began at St. Mary's Church and The Church of Our Saviour.
      Continues to write Marjorie Renison, but doesn't visit.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1929 (5, 12)
      Notes his daily schedule which includes visits to hospital, where he ate dinner, and who he writes, but doesn't mention parishioners names unless he does something socially with them.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1930 (5, 13)
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1931 (5, 14)
      Rev. Sayre's 38th Birthday is on December 18.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1932 (5, 15)
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1933 (5, 16)
      A May 27, 1933 program "Historical Pageant" "Events in the History of the Episcopal Church in The United States of America"¦" given at Christ Church, Media Pennsylvania is in front of diary.
      On August 18, Rev. Sayre arrives in Eagle Rock, Los Angeles, California where Marjorie Renison and her family live. Rev. Sayre and Marjorie Renison go to Laguna Beach together and stay almost a week. Rev. Sayre writes "It's wonderful to be here alone with Miss Renison" and on August 19th, Rev. Sayre writes ""¦I kissed and hugged Marjorie in the gallery."
      On August 30, Rev. Sayre visits Edward Vance's grave, the young man who died while Rev. Sayre cared for him when he was in the Naval Reserve Force.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1934 (5, 17)
      This folder also has newspaper clippings of the September 1933 engagement and the January 13, 1934 wedding in St. John's Episcopal Church in Hampton, Virginia of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre and Marjorie Renison. On June 19th, Marjorie goes on a visit to California and returns September 26. Rev. Sayre goes to conference in Virginia in early July, then to Hampton until mid August. On October 11, Rev. Sayre changed his Life Insurance policies over to Marjorie and borrows money to furnish living room.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1935 (5, 18)
      Slips of sheet music are in the back of the diary.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1936 (5, 19)
      Post cards and addresses are in front of the diary.
      On March 18th the town of Williamsport flooded, including downtown, churches and homes. He goes into detail about the damage on March 20th. On August 3, at the end of a trip to Colorado, Marjorie heads to Los Angeles and Rev. Sayre drives to Pennsylvania. Marjorie returns November 24th.
    - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1937 (5, 20)
      Rev. Sayre includes January 1 through 9, 1938 at end of diary. A letter from Charles Lavery, enclosing a carbon copy of his letter to Rt. Rev. Irving Peake Johnson, is with the diary plus a few news clippings, a list of publications, possibly ones that Rev. Sayre receives and a letter that accompanied a salary check.
- (6)
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1938 and 1939 (6, 21)
    Beginning in 1938, Rev. Sayre uses a journal instead of a one year diary.
    In front of the diary are news clippings, notes, articles, letters and flyers. One flyer is for Altar Wines from James Moroney of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and one clipping announces his resignation from St. Mary's Episcopal Church on October 1 to become rector of St. John's Church, Bellefonte and gives a brief biography of his ministry up to that point.
    He begins the new larger diary ""¦giving a fuller and more detailed account of my daily activities"¦of my personal impressions of people, places and things and events, too"¦"
    Rev. Sayre then summarizes his other diaries, beginning with 1917. He divides the earlier diaries into "Babyhood", "Boyhood", "Youth" and "Young Manhood" periods.
    He gives more detail of events that he recorded in these early diaries, such as a conflict with Dr. George Thomas of St. Paul's Church in Kenwood, Chicago and the effects of the Depression on St. Mary's Church in Pennsylvania. On Page 10, he gives a wonderful description of Marjorie Renison Sayre, his wife.
    The 1938 diary begins his "Manhood" period.
    His early entries are more in depth and personal, even giving detail of things that happened in the past, or people, such as his Mother, but he quickly reverts to just telling of his daily activities with few personal touches.
    Rev. Sayre mentions listening to the new presiding Bishop, Rt. Rev. Henry St. George Tucker of Virginia, on the radio on New Year's Day, 1938.
    He writes "Rev. Dr. W.A.R. Goodwin of Williamsburg, Virginia" on January 10, 1938 and spends the day with him on April 27, 1938.
    Gives resignation to St. Mary's Church and The Church of Our Saviour and meets with Vestry of both churches on July 21, 1938. On September 29, 1938, Marjorie and Samuel Sayre move to Bellefonte, Pennsylvania where he is the new Priest of St. John's Episcopal Church.
    June 8, 1939 Rev. Sayre receives official call to become rector of St. Barnabas Church, Eagle Rock, California where he would succeed his father-in-law, Rev. George E. Renison. On June 13th, he talks to his Mother about it. He hands in his resignation at the St. John's Vestry meeting on July 31, 1939. His last service was on Sunday, October 1 and he began October 15th at St. Barnabas. Grandmother Renison is to live with them in the Parish House per October 23rd entry.
    On August 18, 1939, Rev. Sayre and his family, while he is visiting Newport News, learn that his brother, Dan, who has been in the State Institution in Pennhurst near Spring City, Pennsylvania due to a brain injury at birth, is ill. He dies on August 19, 1939.
    Talks about his parents on January 20, 1937.
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1940 to 1942 (6, 22)
    This volume has postcards of hotels and other notes scattered throughout it.
    Begins on January 1, 1940 where he writes of eventually wanting to retire in Virginia. He gives detail of his cross country trip to Virginia in the summer of 1940. He mentions first blackout in Los Angeles, California on December 10, 1941, a few days after Pearl Harbor on December 7.
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary 1943 to April 29, 1946 (6, 23)
    The folder includes a sermon, letters, clippings, list of people's names with death and baptismal dates, church bulletins, and programs from the Occidental College Art Series. They have been placed in a separate folder in front of the diary and the date where they were located noted.
    On March 4, 1945, Rev. Sayre writes that St. Barnabas' Church was consecrated. He mentions on August 14, 1945 that Japan accepted the surrender terms of the Allies and the city went wild. He had a "Vision After Victory" special service on August 19, 1945. On January 28, 1946, Rev. Sayre writes that his Mother and sister Margaret and husband returned to Hampton where they rented an apartment. They had lived in Salem, Virginia during the war years to be away from the Atlantic Coast.
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary May 1, 1946 to August 31, 1949 (6, 24)
    Rev. Sayre's Mother dies on July 29, 1948 while he is at Orkney Springs, Virginia. On this date, Rev. Sayre inserted a copy of a letter to Marjorie's parents where he talks of the funeral.
    In late July and August, the Sam and Marjorie Sayre travel along the west coast. Many postcards and flyers were inserted between these pages.
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary May 1, 1946 to August 31, 1949, Insertions (6, 25)
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary September 1, 1949 to December 31, 1952 (6, 26)
    There is a hole (mouse nibble) between pages 109 and 195, but very little writing is affected. On December 3, 1950, there is a dedication service for the Canon Robert Renison Memorial Parish House, named in honor of Marjorie's grandfather. Marjorie's father, Rev. George E. Renison, died on January 17, 1951.
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary September 1, 1949 to December 31, 1952, Insertions (6, 27)
  - Rev. Samuel H. Sayre Diary November 1, 1959 to October 31, 1963 (6, 28)
    Rev. Sayre receives a call to become rector of Kingston Parish, Mathews, Virginia on September 6, 1960.
    On November 15, 1960, Rev. Sayre notes that he "tendered his resignation as rector of St. Barnabas' Church" as of January 16, 1961 because of a call from Kingston Parish, Mathews, Virginia. On January 21, 1961, Rev. Sayre renewed his priesthood vows at St. Barnabas. His last Sunday as Rector was February 12, 1961. Rev. Sayre writes about everything he and Marjorie did as they prepared to move to Virginia such as packing and the last vestry meeting, then writes of their trip and all the things they did when they finally arrived in Mathews. November 19, 1962, Rev. Sayre tells about a disappointing Vestry meeting. He is 69 on December 18, 1962.